一只丽龟
An olive ridley turtle.
正在哥斯达黎加的浅水区休息
She's resting in the shallows off Costa Rica,
为了到这儿 它已经游了上千英里
having swum a thousand miles to be here.
只因为它的蛋必须孵在干燥的陆地上
All because the eggs she carries must be laid on dry land.
现在 它又回到了十年前
Now she's returned to the very same beach
那片曾经孵化她的沙滩上
where she hatched 10 years ago.
它必须离开相对安全的海洋
She must leave the safety of her marine world
勇敢去面对前方未知的世界
and brave the alien world beyond.
虽然身怀六甲
She's heavily laden
但它肩负着下一代的命运
but the future of the next generation of her kind is at stake.
在沙滩沿岸 这一壮观的景象
All along the beach in a spectacle that has remained unchanged
几百年来未曾改变
for millions or years,
海龟妈妈们浮出海面
mother sea turtles emerge from the ocean
成千上万
in their hundreds of thousands.
只有那些能克服
Only those animals that overcome the great challenges
海陆两地艰难险阻的动物
of both land and sea
才能到达海岸 完成生命中最重要的使命
can make the most of life here on the coasts.
海岸是个瞬息万变 馈赠丰厚的地方
Our shores are places of sudden changes and rich rewards.
加拉帕戈斯群岛位于热带太平洋上
The Galapagos Islands in the tropical Pacific Ocean.
这个荒芜的海岸看似并不宜居
Their barren coastline looks inhospitable,
但有那么一群动物却能很好地适应
but one group of animals has learnt to use it to their advantage.
海狮
Sea lions.
单身汉们
Bachelors.
他们需要快速增加体重
They need to pile on the pounds
因为只有体格最大的雄海狮 才能吸引雌性与其交配
as only the biggest males will attract a female and manage to breed.
如果这些年轻的海狮长得不够大
If these young bulls fail to grow big enough,
他们就要在这偏僻的海岸线上继续流浪
they will remain exiled on this isolated shoreline.
一只饥肠辘辘的小海狮独自出发了
So one hungry young bull heads out alone.
它开始寻找饕餮盛宴了
He's on the hunt for big game.
一群黄鳍金枪鱼
Yellowfin tuna.
每条黄鳍金枪鱼重达60公斤
Each weighing 60 kilos
时速最快可达40英里(约64km/h)
with a top speed of 40 miles an hour.
在外海 海狮几乎抓不到它们
He can't possibly catch one in the open sea,
但是海狮有一个妙计
but he has a plan.
不远处就是海湾的入口
Ahead lies the entrance to the cove.
他引诱着黄鳍金枪鱼
He herds them towards it
掉入他的陷阱
into his trap.
试图把它们逼到死胡同
Driving them into a dead end.
但黄鳍金枪鱼躲掉了
But they give him the slip.
小海狮失败了
He's failed.
不过天无绝人之路
But there might be another way.
现在海狮成群结队出动
Now they head off as a team
来围捕更多的金枪鱼
to round up more tuna,
并把它们逼进海湾
driving them back into the cove.
海狮将金枪鱼赶到了狭口处
The sea lions fan out channelling the tuna towards the bottleneck.
金枪鱼又一次回到了死胡同
Once again the tuna hit the dead end.
但是这一次 年轻的雄海狮
But this time, the young bull doubles back
封锁了出口
to act as a blocker sealing off the exit.
一旦有鱼群想逃跑
This time when the shoal tries to escape,
海狮又会把它们逼进下一个死胡同
he blocks them and drives them back into the next blind alley.
现在海狮可以把它们依次解决了
The gang can now pick them off one by one.
这个聪明的围捕技术
This clever fishing technique,
需要极强的战略眼光和通力合作
demanding foresight, planning and cooperation,
也只有在加拉帕戈斯群岛才可以看到
has only every been seen here in the Galapagos.
一条大金枪鱼能提供的蛋白质含量
Each massive fish provides them with five times more protein
就是平日捕猎一天所汲取的五倍
than a normal day's hunting.
最后 这只年轻的海狮离开了他的岗位
Finally, the young bull leaves his post
开始享用它的战利品
to claim his reward.
以这些蛋白质丰富的金枪鱼为食
On a diet of protein-rich tuna,
这只小海狮很快就会成长为强壮的雄性海狮
he's well on the way to becoming a full-sized breeding bull.
利用这个海湾
By using this cove,
加拉帕戈斯群岛的海狮们
these Galapagos sea lions have made the most of the opportunities
充分把握了这得天独厚的优势
that occur where the coast's two worlds meet.
因为潮起潮落 海岸是所有海洋栖息地中
Coasts are the most swiftly changing of all ocean habitats
最为变化多端的
because of the tides.
潮汐是月球引力作用于大海产生的
Tides are created as the moon's gravity pulls at the sea.
月球的公转带来了潮起潮落
As the moon circles our planet, the seas rise and fall.
通常一天两次
Typically twice a day,
造就了地球上最长久的动态景观
creating the most constantly dynamic landscapes on Earth.
也只有这里的海洋生物 需要面对如此多变的生存环境
Nowhere else do sea-living creatures face such changeable conditions.
它们每天都要冒着被太阳炙烤烘干的危险
With the daily risk of drying out and being scorched by the sun.
岩岸在潮汐退去后
Where the tide retreats across a rocky shore,
会留下一片临时乐土
it can leave behind a temporary oasis.
潮水潭
A rock pool.
这里看似宁静的一隅
Seemingly, it's a haven of calm.
但好景不长
But not for long.
将镜头放快便可以看到意想不到的场景
Turning minutes into seconds reveals unexpected dramas.
潮水潭里的食草动物 食腐动物和滤食性动物
In rock pools, grazers, scavengers and filter feeders
必须在涨潮前
must all make the most of the few short hours
充分利用这数个小时
before the tide returns.
海葵吞下了触手可及的一切东西
Anemones gulp down anything they can reach.
尽管有些时候这些东西很难消化
Though some meals are harder to digest than others.
这个魔法世界很快就变成了战场
These magical worlds soon become battlegrounds.
这个致命的猎食者 它有五只触手 加之底部的一张嘴
A deadly predator with five arms and on the underside a mouth.
赭色海星
The ochre starfish.
它正在寻找帽贝
And it's in search of limpets.
对于有的帽贝而言 它们无处可逃
For some, there is no escape.
海星吞噬了它们
It engulfed them.
但是有的帽贝有秘密的防御武器
But other limpets have a secret defense.
它们将套膜外翻作为防御盾
They deploy a slippery shield
使海星失去立足点继而逃脱
which allows them to slide to safety.
这只帽贝有一个私人保镖
And this limpet has its own personal bodyguard.
一只咬合力极强的海鳞虫
A scale worm with a nasty nip.
这只海星还是喜欢吃些不咬人的食物
The starfish prefers food that doesn't bite back.
帽贝继续前行
The limpet carries on,
它的保镖在其壳下得到庇护
its bodyguard tucked safe under its shell.
但是有一种生物
But there is one creature
让帽贝束手无策
that limpets have no defense against.
那就是喉盘鱼
A clingfish.
它的牙可以撬动帽贝的壳
It has teeth that can lever under the shell
像拧瓶盖一样旋下帽贝
and twist the limpet off like a bottle top.
喉盘鱼吞下了它
The clingfish then swallows it
连壳一起
shell and all.
这样的戏码在潮水潭里仅能上演数个小时
Rock pool dramas like these last just a few short hours
随后潮水便会涨起
before the tide returns.
大海每天潮起潮落
Every day the sea becomes land and the land becomes sea.
带来新的机遇
Bringing new opportunities.
莎莉飞毛腿蟹
A Sally Lightfoot crab,
作为成百上千食草蟹中的一种
one of thousands of shore crabs
它们正等待着属于自己的时刻
just waiting for their moment.
它们每天都聚集在巴西的热带海岸上
Every day they gather on the tropical shores of Brazil,
等待退潮的那一刻
waiting for the tide to go out.
将它们的觅食地展现出来
Which exposes their feeding ground,
覆盖着海藻的岩石 离岸边一百多米远
seaweed covered rocks, a hundred metres from the shore.
到达那里是一场与潮汐的赛跑
Getting there is a race against the tide.
它们从一块石头跳到另一块石头上
They leap from rock to rock.
这些螃蟹似乎很怕水
These crabs seem to be afraid of the water.
这也事出有因
And for good reason.
海鳝
The Moray eel.
链蛇鳝是捕蟹专家
The chain Moray is a specialist crab hunter.
它的钝齿可以轻易地抓住并压碎螃蟹的壳
It's blunt teeth can easily grip and crush a crab's shell.
它是螃蟹最致命的敌人
It's the crab's deadliest enemy.
但距离觅食地螃蟹还有很长的路要走
But the crab's feeding grounds are still a long way off.
它们必须坚持下去
They must press on.
路程已半
Halfway.
但它们的天敌别有妙招
But their enemy has other ideas.
穿过陆地
Crossing the land
重设伏击
to reset the ambush.
为了觅食 这些螃蟹不得不继续前行
To feed, the crabs must keep going.
但是危险无处不在
But nowhere is safe.
章鱼也是螃蟹的天敌
An octopus. Also a crab killer.
螃蟹勇往直前
The crabs make a dash for it.
它成功脱逃了
Made it.
冒着生命危险
Risking life and limb
终于吃到了海藻
to graze on these seaweed pastures.
但两个小时后又要涨潮了
But in two hours' time when the tide starts to turn,
它们不得不再次面对严酷挑战
they will have to run the gauntlet all over again.
潮汐并不是冲击海岸的唯一力量
Tides are not the only force to have an impact on the coasts.
来自远海的惊涛骇浪
The greatest waves originate far out to sea
滚滚而来 咆哮着涌向海岸
and roll in towards the coast, growing as they come.
在浅海海床的抬升下
As the shallowing sea floor drags at their underside,
波峰可以上升到一百英尺高(约30.5米)
their crests rise up to a hundred feet high,
巨浪倾覆进而平息
topple over and break.
葡萄牙的扎雷所属海域 曾诞生了
Many of the biggest surfed waves in the world
许多被冲浪选手征服过的世界级大浪
are formed off Nazare in Portugal.
纳扎雷海岸每天的海浪冲击力
Every day along this coast, the impact of the waves is equivalent
都相当于150万吨TNT炸药爆炸
to one and a half million tonnes of TNT.
也正是浪潮的冲击渐渐塑造了我们的海岸
Wave power gradually moulds and reshapes our coasts.
在欧洲的一些地方
In some parts of Europe,
海浪每年冲蚀的海岸线长达3米
waves wear away as much as three metres of coastline each year.
海浪重塑岩石的速率
The rate at which the waves reshape the rock
取决于岩石自身的硬度
depends on its hardness.
当软岩分布在硬岩下方时
Where soft rock lies below hard,
就会形成奇特的拱形石
dramatic arches are craved.
在西班牙北海岸
It's an endless assault
海浪永不停歇的拍打敲击
that gradually sculpts vaulted cathedrals of stone
逐渐雕刻出一个个拱形的石头教堂
as here in northern Spain.
这些位于北极的悬崖峭壁
And wave power creates towering fortresses
正是海浪为数万只海鸟
like these cliffs in these Arctic,
打造的天然栖息堡垒
home to tens of thousands of breeding seabirds.
悬崖的正面只能从空中到达
The faces of the cliffs are accessible only from the air
其中有充足的角落和缝隙 供抵达的生物落脚
and have plenty of nooks and crannies for those that can get there.
但为了觅食 海鸟还必须要掌控海洋的世界
But to feed, seabirds must still master the ocean world beyond.
北极海鹦
The puffin.
他是名渔夫
He's a fisherman...
也是个父亲
...and a father.
这是他的伴侣
He has a mate for life.
它们共同担负起养育小海鹦的重任
Both share the burden of raising their week-old chick,
一周大的小海鹦 每天需要投喂五次
their puffling who needs five square meals a day.
它的父母轮流出海捕鱼
The parents alternate fishing trips.
现在轮到爸爸了
It's dad's turn.
当鱼类数量较少时
When fish stocks are low,
海鹦必须出海飞行30多英里(约48km)
puffins must fly as much as 30 miles out sea
才能到达渔场
to reach the good fishing grounds.
随后便潜入另一片新天地
Once there,they plunge into another world.
良好的捕鱼点很难占据 并且它们有竞争对手
Good fishing spots are hard to come by, and they have company.
海鸠
Guillemots.
跟海鹦一样 它们的翅膀很短 适合潜水
Like the puffin, their wings are short and good for diving.
海鹦能屏息超过一分钟
Puffins can hold their breath for over a minute
并能潜入40米深的水域
and dive as deep as 40 metres.
抓到一条
A catch.
但归途漫漫
But it's a long way home.
在飞越长达60英里(约97km)的艰辛路途后
After an exhausting round trip of almost 60 miles,
这只海鹦就快要成功了
this puffin's nearly made it.
但海岸线还有海盗虎视眈眈
But there are pirates on this coast.
北极贼欧
Arctic Skuas.
所有回家的父母都会遭受抢劫
All around returning parents are being robbed.
贼欧因有长且向后倾斜的翅膀
The skuas' long rake back wings
飞行更为迅速敏捷
make them faster and more manoeuvrable.
海鹦们必须得明智地把握时机
Puffins must choose their moment wisely.
一次惊险的逃脱
A near miss.
拼尽全力进行最后冲刺
A last desperate burst of speed,
它成功了
and it's made it.
历经三小时的往返
Safely home after a three-hour round trip...
在伴侣耐心的等待中 平安到家
...where his patient partner is waiting.
今天小海鹦将饱餐一顿
Today their puffling will eat.
但在鱼类资源衰减的地区
But where fish numbers are in decline,
许多海鹦很难为雏鸟捕获充足的食物
many puffins now find it hard to get enough food for their chicks.
在海洋生态每况愈下的今天
In the changing seas of today,
想做成功的海鹦父母更加艰难
it can be even harder to be a successful puffin parent.
同时接受两种空间的挑战很不容易
Overcoming the challenges of two worlds is seldom easy.
有一种海洋生物几乎完全脱离了海洋
One marine creature has virtually abandoned the sea altogether.
在几个偏远的太平洋岛屿上
On a few remote pacific islands,
生活着地球上最爱在陆地生活的鱼
lives the most terrestrial fish on the planet.
在这个数米高石灰岩悬崖的顶端
At the top of this metre-high limestone cliff,
一只八厘米长的岩跳鱼已经拥有了一个巢穴
an eight-centimetre long blenny has chosen a nest hole.
在这里 他可以安心在充足的海藻上生活
Up here, he can graze on the abundant algae
没有任何海水鱼类与它竞争
without any competition from sea-going fish.
一群雌性岩跳鱼在他下方觅食
The females are feeding beneath him.
他渴望引起她们的注意
He's keen to attract their attention,
但她们正忙着保湿
but they are busy moisturising.
保持湿润非常重要 因为它们通过皮肤呼吸
Staying damp is essential as they breathe through their skin.
为了使自己更具吸引力 他变成了黑色
To make himself conspicuous,he turns black
并不断抖动橙色的鳍
and flashes his orange fin.
他终于吸引了她的眼球
He catches her eye.
但这些太平洋跳跃好手
But these Pacific leaping blennies,
似乎很害怕海浪
seem afraid of the waves.
它们不擅长游泳
They're poor swimmers
并很容易在海中被捕食
and will be easy prey in the sea.
再试一次
Time to try again.
她心动了
She's tempted.
但海浪再次扫了兴
But once again distracted by a wave.
雄性岩跳鱼没有放弃
The male just won't give up.
最终 她着迷了
Finally, she's hooked.
他把路让开
He makes way...
让她能顺利进入他的巢穴
so she can enter his cave.
并用他诱人的舞蹈
And he encourages her to lay her eggs
鼓励她在此产卵
with his seductive dance.
然后 他在安全的巢穴中给这些卵受精
He then fertilizes them in the safety of his nest.
岩跳鱼为了陆地上的生活放弃了海洋
The blenny has given up the sea for a life on land.
有种生物在另一领域内
Others have made an even more successful move
有了更成功的实践
but in a different direction.
企鹅放弃了飞行
Penguins have abandoned flying
并用大半生的时间来游泳
and instead spend most of their lives swimming.
它们的羽毛像光滑的救生衣
Their sleek survival suits of tightly packed feathers
非常适合在冰冷的水域遨游
are perfect for these freezing waters.
但是它们一年还是要上岸一次
Yet, they must still come ashore once a year.
这里是靠近南极洲的南乔治亚岛
South Georgia, an island wilderness close to Antarctica.
每年春天 成千上万的王企鹅回到这里
Each spring, its beaches become the busiest on Earth
使这片海滩成为地球上最繁忙的地方
as hundreds of thousands of king penguins return here.
他们正在前往聚集地
They're heading for the colony.
但他们要穿过这世界上最大的肉体墙壁
But in their way lies the biggest wall of blubber on the planet.
象海豹
Elephant seals.
现在正是繁殖的季节
It's the breeding season
重达四吨的"公牛"们 正为他们的女眷相互搏斗
and the four-tonne bulls are fighting for control of their harems.
最好等待他们冷静下来
Best to wait for them to calm down.
他不能从这障碍上飞过去
He can't fly over this barrier,
只能尽量轻声漫步 降低自己的存在感
so he will have to walk as unobtrusively as possible.
并希望沉睡的巨人不要醒来
And hope that sleeping giants will continue to lie.
小心
Careful.
麻烦来了
This could be tricky.
一头雄性象海豹被对手挑衅
A rival bull mounts a challenge.
企鹅可能会被卷入这场交火中
The penguins could be caught in the crossfire.
八吨脂肪相撞
Eight tonnes of blubber collide.
这只高大的搏击大师取得胜利
The towering beach master is victorious.
这只企鹅在疑惑中悄悄溜走
In the confusion,this penguin slips through.
前面有4万只小企鹅
Ahead are 40,000 chicks.
饥饿并兴奋着
Hungry and over-excited.
但并不是每只企鹅都有孩子要喂
But not every penguin has a chick to feed.
他们并非为此而来
That's not why they're here.
而是另有目的
There is another reason.
每个企鹅都要面临一场对耐力的考验
There is a trial of endurance that every penguin must face,
这个考验的开始 就是持续的瘙痒
and it starts with a persistent itch.
他的救生服已经在
His survival suit has been worn thin
为期数月的南大洋游泳中磨损
by months of swimming in the rough southern ocean.
解决方案很粗暴
His solution is drastic.
尽快把四层羽毛都蜕下来
Shed all four layers of feathers as quickly as possible.
这个过程被称为毁坏式脱毛
The process is known as a catastrophic moult.
在新的羽毛生出之前
Until their feathers regrow,
企鹅要一直驻扎在此地
penguins will remain rooted to the spot.
已经挨饿一个月了
Having starved for a month,
它们现在不能碰水 再次与世隔绝
they're now fully waterproofed and insulated once more.
饥饿使它们迫切回到海中的生活
Lean, hungry and eager to return to a life at sea.
得力于它们防水的羽毛
Thanks to their waterproof plumage,
企鹅能充分利用两种空间存活
penguins are able to make the most of both worlds
即使在地球上最恶劣的环境下也是如此
even in some of the harshest conditions on Earth.
南乔治亚岛的海岸
The coasts of South Georgia
由于地处偏远 受到了保护
are currently protected by their remoteness.
其他海岸线则脆弱的多
Other coastlines are much more vulnerable,
现在它们的变化速度 比以往任何时候都快
and they are now changing faster than ever before.
有三分之二的主要城市都位于海岸线上
Two thirds of our major cities are on our coasts.
据估计 未来十年
It's estimated that in the next decade,
全球剩余的原生态海岸中约有10%
we can expect 10% of the world's remaining wild shores
将被人工开发
to be taken over by human development.
然而每年 只要沿着佛罗里达的棕榈海滩走一走
Yet every year, just off Florida's Palm Beach
就能发现许多无人留意的壮丽景象
and extraordinary spectacle appears almost unnoticed.
那就是地球上最大的沿海鲨鱼种群
The biggest gathering of coastal sharks on the planet.
短鳍真鲨和黑鳍鲨
Spinners and blacktips.
足有一万头之多
Ten thousand of them.
每年一月 它们寻找这些气候温暖的浅海
Every January, they seek out these warm shallows
以便在北上迁移的途中作短暂停留
as a stopover on their migration northwards.
鲨鱼们早在人类踏足这里之前 就开始在此地聚集了
Sharks have been gathering here since long before people arrived.
但如今 它们面临着大量的污染
But today, they face levels of pollution
栖息地的恶化以及海洋捕鱼的威胁
and habitat degradation as well as fishing pressures.
而这些是它们祖先从未遭遇过的
that their ancestors would never have experienced.
海岸生物主宰自己地盘的日子
It's not longer enough for coastal creatures
已然一去不复返了
to master their own worlds.
现如今又要面临来自我们人类世界的种种挑战
Now they must face the many challenges that come from our world, too.
为了拍摄最奇妙的沿海生物
To film the most surprising coastal wildlife,
蓝色星球II的团队
the Blue Planet II team
来到了地球上最偏远的几处海岸
travelled to some of the remotest shores on the planet.
其中之一就是加拉帕戈斯群岛
One destination was the Galapagos islands.
在这里 他们从当地摄影师理查德 乌勒克姆
Here they were in search of an almost unbelievable story
口中挖掘出一个奇迹般的故事
brought to them by a local cameraman Richard Wollocombe.
这件事还是我听我的一个
Well, I was talking to a friend of mine
当地的渔夫朋友说的
who's a fisherman over here,
他说某一次他来到这个海湾的时候
and he said that one day he turned up here in this bay,
忽然看见一群海狮正在追捕金枪鱼群
and suddenly he saw a group of sea lions chasing these massive tuna
直追到海滩上
up onto the beach.
我当时想"编得真有意思 我才不信呢"
And I was like, "Yeah, funny one. I don't believe a word of that."
那听起来太不可思议了
That just sounds too unreal.
但是渔夫的故事太诱人了
Still the lure of the fisherman's tale
以至于我们很难忽略它
was too great to ignore.
我有点紧张 如果那不是真的话
I'm a little nervous that if it doesn't happen,
我的名声可就不保了
there goes my credibility.
蓝色星球II团队开始了地毯式的考察
The Blue Planet II team launch a full-scale expedition,
但是一名成员仍将信将疑
but one of them is still skeptical.
如果海狮真的会去捕猎金枪鱼的话
It's gonna be pretty spectacular if...
那将是非常惊人的场景
if a sea lion could actually chase down and kill a tuna.
总之我是不信
I'm still yet to be convinced.
他们在这片荒芜的小海湾搭起了帐篷
They set up camp in this barren cove,
作为接下来一个月的住所
home for the next month.
当地的野生动物出了名的温顺
The local wildlife, famed for its tameness,
它们对自己的新邻居充满好奇
is curious to meet its new neighbours.
虽然尚未发现海狮的踪迹
With no sign of the sea lions,
全体成员还是用远距离水下摄像机监视着这片海湾
the crew stake out the cove with remote underwater cameras.
现场助理罗比 派普勒斯值第一轮班
Field assistant Roby Pepolas takes first watch.
这里就是
This is the point of view
我们用来观察海狮
where we try to see the sea lions come in
从水中跳出来的地点
jumping over the water.
如果海狮们距离非常近的话
If they're definitely coming very close,
他们就会说"行动起来"或者"一起摇摆"
they say, "Action, action," or "Rock and roll."
三小时后
Three hours later...
航空摄像组是最先行动起来的
The aerial team are first up.
这是一只海狮正把金枪鱼群赶进海湾
It's a sea lion chasing tuna into the bay.
噢 它捕到了
Oh, he's got it. He's got it.
难以置信
Unbelievable!
看那儿 他还在挣扎
Look at that, he's still struggling.
天哪
Holy moly!
被挣脱了
He's lost him.
金枪鱼溜走了
The tuna gives the sea lion the slip.
接下来的几天里 更多海狮来到这片海湾
Over the coming days, more sea lions arrive in the cove
捕猎黄鳍金枪鱼
chasing in yellowfin tuna.
对 对 对
Yeah, yeah, yeah, ooh!
我敢打赌肯定会有更多的金枪鱼和海狮过来
I bet you there's more tuna and another sea lion.
那片小水洼里大概有六条金枪鱼
There's like six tuna in that bay.
一头海狮引起了理查德的注意
One sea lion has caught Richard's attention,
他亲切地称呼它为泰格博
and he's affectionately called him Tagboy.
它与众不同 是个经验丰富的老猎手
He's really different. He's, like, a prolific hunter,
并且格外灵巧
and he's really agile.
有它出现的镜头都很精彩
It's just fascinating to watch and see the picture emerge about who he is.
自空中俯瞰的无人机显示了
From above, the drone is revealing
海狮是如何聚在一起捕猎的
how the group of sea lions are hunting together.
从空中我们可以真切地看到海狮的进攻战略
From the air, we really see the strategy of the sea lion
并且可以明显看出它们的分工
and see them with their individual roles as well.
泰格博待在水渠中央
Tagboy stays off in the middle of the channel
防止有金枪鱼逃脱
to make sure none of them escape.
每只海狮都扮演自己的角色
Everyone's got a role
它们形成了一个真正的团队
and they're really a team in bringing them together.
尽管海狮们一直在浅水区捕猎
Although the sea lions have been hunting in the shallows,
大家还是看到它们将一条金枪鱼驱赶到海滩上
the crew are yet to see them drive a tuna onto the beach.
糟糕的是 海狮们并非这里唯一的狩猎者
And to make matters worse, the sea lions aren't alone in this cove.
这里还有足足两米长的加拉帕戈斯鲨鱼
Galapagos sharks, each two metres long.
这些鲨鱼几乎游到了海滩上
The shark almost beached itself
并且从大海狮那里偷走了金枪鱼
and stole the tuna from the big sea lion,
海狮懊恼不已
who is now really angry.
尽管水中有鲨鱼
Despite the sharks,
为了拍摄到整个画面 理查德必须进入海水中
to reveal the full story, Richard needs to get in the water.
鲨鱼捕猎的惯用伎俩 靠海水中的血迹
Classic shark attack scenario. Blood in the water, shallow,
他们很容易认错对象
and easy mistaken identity.
当心你的手 罗比
Watch your hands, Roby.
工作人员们穿了防护服以保护自己
The crew gain some protection from chain mail suits.
简直是鲨鱼派对了
now a shark pool.
一 二 三 四 五 现在有六条鲨鱼了
One, two, three, four, five, six sharks now.
海水中大量的血让这些鲨鱼近乎疯狂
With so much blood in the water, the sharks go into a feeding frenzy.
瞬间就把金枪鱼撕成了碎片
Make mince meat of these tuna in seconds.
坦白讲 这么近距离地观察
To be so close to something so unbelievably ferocious
如此凶残和危险的画面
and dangerous, quite frankly,
真的很奇妙
is amazing. It's... It's...
能躲在这后面真是太好了
It's nice to be able to hide behind all this though.
然而 活跃了一个星期以后
But then, after a week of increasing activity,
海狮忽然停止了捕猎
the sea lions suddenly stop fishing.
自从我们开始观察以来
It's the first day though
这是我们第一次
that we haven't seen any action
一整天都没有看到任何海狮活动
during the whole day. Since we start.
我们有点儿担心
We are kind of worried.
金枪鱼消失了
The tuna have disappeared.
理查德十分担忧
Richard is worried.
种种迹象表明
The signs are starting to show
随着海洋变暖 它们的活动越来越少
across the globe that the seas are warming, they're becoming less productive.
加拉帕戈斯的海洋生物需要不断翻滚上涌的
Galapagos marine life relies on cold, deep currents
上升寒流来不断补充水面的营养物质
welling up intermittently to fertilize the surface waters.
如果海水上涌变得不那么频繁
If those upwellings become less consistent,
这些生物将处于危险的境地
er, their lives could well be in jeopardy.
过去
In the past,
每当寒流上涌暂时停止的时候
when these cold water upwellings have temporarily stopped,
大量海狮就会被饿死
many sea lions have starved to death.
而温暖的海水更会削弱这些上升流
And a warming ocean could further weaken these upwellings.
两个周的焦急等待过后
Then after two weeks of nervous waiting,
出现了转机
a hopeful sign.
一场大雾降临在这片海湾
A thick fog descends over the cove.
开始有寒流翻滚 上涌
We've got very cold water that's come up, upwelled,
并蔓延到整片海域
and spread across the ocean,
这些冷水和温暖的空气相遇 产生了大雾
and mixed with the warm air, creating the fog
我们希望这些冷水
and hoping that this cold water
能缓解目前的困境 让海狮的捕猎重新开始
will just kick things off a bit, you know, and get the action going.
当浓雾渐渐散去 振奋人心的场景出现了
As the fog clears, a welcome sight...
金枪鱼群回到了这里 海狮们紧随其后
The tuna are back with sea lions hot on their heels.
工作人员立刻行动起来
The crew leap into action.
在水里
Being in the water,
理查德可以跟拍海狮的团队行动
Richard can at last follow the sea lions' teamwork
最终他拍到了泰格博将一条金枪鱼拖上岸的画面
and finally film Tagboy beaching a tuna.
它们了解这迷宫一样的地形
The know the bottlenecks in this labyrinth.
它们知道如何将猎物引入这些狭道之中
They know how to push them into those bottlenecks
正是泰格博
and threre was just Tagboy,
用它巨大的身躯封住了入口
almost his entire body was blocking the entrance,
它只是优雅地来回游动 就让金枪鱼筋疲力尽
and he was just gently back and forth tiring the fish out.
绝对令人惊叹 非常非常震撼人心
Absolutely extraordinary. Really, really impressive.
蕾切尔导演
Director Rachel
对海狮油然而生一股赞叹
has a newfound respect for the sea lions.
我从不知道它们能够
I had no idea they were capable
达到这种程度的组织和团队协作
of this level of planning and strategy and teamwork.
我从不知道它们如此聪明
I had no idea they were this intelligent.
理查德成功地拍摄到了这场独特的捕猎行动
Richard has succeeded in filming this unique hunting strategy
这证明了渔夫所言非虚
and in doing so has proved the fisherman's tale to be true.
海狮拥有让人难以置信的高智商
The sea lions' intelligence is unbelievably sophisticated.
这远远超出了我的想象
So to say that my expectations have been exceeded is a sight understatement.
这是我在加拉帕戈斯群岛度过的
This is been one of the most remarkable times
最让人印象深刻的日子之一
I've ever had here in the Galapagos.
下一次
Next time...
我们将环游世界 来记录人类如今面临的首要海洋问题
We travel the world to uncover the biggest issues facing the ocean...
我们将拜访一群
meet the passionate people
将毕生奉献给保护海洋的人
who've devoted their lives to protecting it
我们也将探索这个蓝色星球的未来
and discover what the future holds for our blue planet.
Translated by
MAGGIE & PINASTER & DAWN
翻译：马小尾 & 小松树 & 顾子熹
Supervised by
VERONICA
监制：斑斑
Proofreaded by
LONG & WILDER
校对：小龙 & 歪二德
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SHOU
特效：歪二德
它就在这里捕食
来这边
理查德·乌勒克姆
摄影师
罗比·派普勒斯
户外助理
丹·比彻姆
无人机摄影师
蕾切尔·巴特勒
导演
海   岸
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(岩跳鱼虽然外表与弹涂鱼[跳跳鱼]很相似,但是岩跳鱼属鳚科而弹涂鱼属虾虎鱼科)
(王企鹅躯体大小仅次于帝企鹅,是南极企鹅中姿势最优雅,性情最温顺,外貌最漂亮的一种)
(海鬣蜥:加拉帕戈斯群岛特有物种 是世界上唯一能适应海洋生活的鬣蜥)
(弱翅鸬鹚:一种大型不能飞行的鸬鹚,为加拉帕戈斯群岛特有物种)
(丽龟:海龟中最小的一种,体长60-70厘米,体重约12千克,分布于整个热带海域)
(哥斯达黎加:位于拉丁美洲的一个总统共和制国家 北邻尼加拉瓜 南与巴拿马接壤)
(又名科隆群岛 隶属厄瓜多尔 位于南美大陆以西1000公里的太平洋面上)
(帽贝牙齿胜过蛛丝,是生物界中已知强度最大的天然物质,其成分甚至可用来做防弹衣)
(喉盘鱼是世界上粘度最大的鱼 其粘合力是其体重的230倍)
(学名红石蟹,是美洲西海岸最常见的螃蟹之一)
远海波浪速度快,动能大,与大陆架碰撞后
海水变浅,水速放缓动能转换为势能,使得其到达陆地岸边时具有较高的高度
(纳扎雷小镇以迷人的海滩和"魔鬼"巨浪闻名于世,每年吸引了大批冲浪爱好者)
(TNT炸药[三硝基甲苯]:一种烈性炸药,需要雷管进行引爆.)